On July 17th, Apple overtook NVIDIA to
become the most valuable company on Earth.
And they did, by essentially ignoring AI.
So… how?
For years,
Apple was mocked for being “behind” on AI.
They spend about 2% of sales on AI,
while the Hyperscalers spend 39%.
They also became the second
company to pass $5 trillion in market cap.
How is Apple winning, by refusing to build AI?
This is how Apple won the AI race… by ignoring it.
Before vs now
This might not sound that surprising.
“Oh Apple is #1 again, what else is new”
But just a few years or even months
ago, you wouldn’t think they’d be here.
From early 2022, all the way to early 2026,
Apple had a bit of a mixed performance.
A big one was last year, where Apple
fell almost 19% between April and May.
Not only were there lawsuits and tariffs on
Chinese components that would now affect Apple,
a big focus was on their lacklustre AI products.
“Siri’s initial promise was to revolutionize user
interaction with Apple devices through voice
commands and intelligent assistance. However,
users have frequently reported frustrations
with Siri’s limited understanding,
lack of contextual awareness, and
inability to perform complex tasks.”
The new “AI powered” Siri which was supposed
to be integrated into your mail, calendar,
messages, was delayed, had hundreds of
bugs, and general underwhelming reception.
So, Apple postponed it indefinitely.
We also got Apple Intelligence,
revealed at WWDC24.
But as it rolled out,
also came more problems.
More delays, more features
postponed, general user dissatisfaction.
Despite this, Apple overpromised what the AI
could actually do, and promoted features that
Apple Intelligence couldn’t even perform yet.
So they discontinued a major TV ad
for the new AI Siri, among others.
The features were then promoted as an
iPhone 17 feature… instead of the iPhone 16.
What added fuel to this AI dumpster
fire, was the leadership collapse.
AI chief John Giannandrea announced
his retirement in December 2025,
over concerns about product direction.
Siri was moved under Mike Rockwell,
who launched the Vision Pro. And
we all know how well that one went.
Then Apple decided to change course.
Apple’s main AI partner, was ChatGPT.
Makes sense, for a while they
seemed like the only AI partner.
But that soon fell apart, and Apple
recently sued OpenAI for trade secret theft.
They instead went with Google
Gemini. A better choice,
but it was also seen as a bit of a self-own.
“The 1.2 trillion parameters of Google’s AI make
Apple’s 150 million parameters for the cloud-based
version of Apple Intelligence almost embarrassing,
and while I have little doubt that Apple, with the
help of Google, will get AI on its devices right,
it’s hard not to ignore the mess that the
Cupertino-based tech giant has found itself in.”
Plus, Google already pays Apple an estimated $20B
a year to be the default Safari search engine.
Apple was now paying Google back.
In a way, it seemed like
Apple was going backwards.
Falling behind the next boom.
Today LLMs are leapfrogging.
Claude jumps slightly ahead,
then GPT, then Gemini.
Plus, they’re all great at different things,
but subscribing to all of them can cost a fortune.
So get all the cutting edge models
with one subscription: Mammouth.
Mammouth gives you access to the best and cutting
edge AI models in one place, for only $10 a month.
Yeah, just $10.
Switch between GPT, Claude, Grok, and even
specialized tools like Perplexity and Nano Banana.
But it’s not just better value,
it's the best way to use AI.
With them all in one place, you can
use Mammouth’s re-prompting feature to
compare results across different models.
If you aren’t satisfied with a response
from ChatGPT, click “reprompt”, and ask
Claude, or Gemini, or Grok, or any other.
No need to be locked into one company.
But it gets better.
Use the Mammouth Agentic mode for more complex
tasks, it can generate or edit documents,
do in-depth web search, and take on multi-task
queries. You can then use the Mammouth API to
integrate these into your own automation tools.
And just like the cutting edge AI platforms,
there’s Mammouth Code for developers, which
integrates right into your native coding console.
Mammouth currently equips more than 400
companies and public administrations with
its dedicated plan. It has great plans
for both individuals and companies.(
Mammouth is also based in Paris, with their
servers hosted in Germany, which means they
are fully GDPR compliant under the European Union.
Stay at the cutting edge of AI without the lock
in, and less of the cost.
Click the url in the
description and try Mammouth today.
Thank you to Mammouth for sponsoring our videos.
Then came the 12th of Feb 2026, where
Apple dropped 5%. Basically wiping
out all the gains Apple had for the year.
This was, you guessed it, due to Siri delays,
when a huge AI update was just weeks from launch.
People were even saying the Magnificent 7 should
be changed to “Mag 6” to exclude Apple.
[Shannon Carroll, Quartz.com]:“Apple was
late to the party, largely relied on
a partner rather than a breakthrough,
and has barely made a dent since. Rollout
has been sluggish, features are still
limited and easily found elsewhere, and
Apple hasn’t announced much else. In a
market moment defined by fast, flashy AI
moves, the company has showed up late”
People were beginning to wonder…
was Apple past its prime?
Which, brings us to today, and it
seems like everything has done a 180.
Why is Apple now at the top again,
if they failed so spectacularly?
Apple somehow climbed back to #1.
They have since dropped down to #2, but
are still ahead of the hyperscalers, way ahead of
Alphabet and Microsoft, who are third and fourth.
Now, there is a counterargument here.
Some would say this is just because NVIDIA
dipped in July, which has now rebounded. That this
doesn’t really have anything to do with Apple.
But, this misses the bigger picture.
On the whole for 2026, Apple is up 24%,
against NVIDIA’s 4%.
Not only that, Apple is up
nearly 60% over the trailing 12 months.
So, yeah it’s true NVIDIA dipped a bit,
but it doesn’t explain Apple’s resurgence.
Why are they still ahead of the hyperscalers,
with such little AI spend?
Or, did people only now
realize that they were right all along?
To understand what’s really going on, we first
need to look at maybe the most important benchmark
right now: Capex (show “capex” on screen).
Aka capital expenditure.
Funds companies spend to acquire,
upgrade, or maintain long-term physical assets.
Apple currently invest roughly 2.5% of their 2026
estimated sales in capital expenditure, or capex.
For the fiscal year 2025, ending September,
Apple’s capex was: $12.7 billion.
With the AI‑related portion estimated
around $11–12.7 billion.
The Fiscal 2026 projections
are around $13–14 billion in AI‑related
capex, only a modest increase from 2025.
Sounds like a lot. I mean,
it’s $13 billion or more…
Until you look at the rest
of the magnificent seven.
Meta’s 2025 capex was $72 billion, with
guidance of $130 to $145B for 2026.
Alphabet was even higher, $80 billion
for 2025, $175 to $205B for 2026.
Microsoft’s was $64 billion in 2025,
estimated $190 billion in 2026.
And the biggest, by far, was Amazon.
$107B in 2025,
and an estimated $200 billion in 2026. Holy moly.
Most of that is towards AWS,
AI datacenters, and NVIDIA GPUs.
Apple’s capex is about 1/10th of Amazon’s,
and less than 1/14th of their 2026 capex.
Most of the Mag 7 together are spending
about $700 billion, and on average are
putting 39% of sales into AI spend.
All except Apple.
Yet, this year they passed
all of these companies, and even NVIDIA.
So… how is it so low? And what’s changed?
Well, we already know part of the answer.
Instead of building their own model, licensing
Gemini has cut down a huge amount of cost.
Paying a billion a year to license instead
of hundreds of billions to build out
your own? Pretty good idea it turns out.
And this is quite important, because
it allows Apple to do something else.
Apple has a very different focus for AI.
[Craig Federighi, at WWDC26] “At Apple,
we believe privacy in AI is non-negotiable.”
Apple actually first introduced this idea
back at WWDC24, when they first introduced
*Private Cloud Compute.* More on that later.
Apple’s core bet right now, is that the most
useful AI should run locally. On your iPhone,
iPad, Mac, not in a remote data centre.
Local AIs are fast, more cost-effective,
and importantly: Private. (show headline).
But, it can’t realistically run
everything locally.
For heavier tasks,
Apple Intelligence uses “Private Cloud Compute.”
Apple does own data centres, and it’s actually
owned them for over a decade, but
for iCloud services, Apple Maps,
the App Store, among other things.
Data centres aren’t just for AI, remember.
So, they refitted some of them for Private Cloud
Compute, for when Apple customers need cloud-based
AI, which Apple charges for.
But not all of it.
For the heaviest workloads, Apple doesn’t
really use any of its own data centres.
They also don’t build out massive data
centres like the other hyperscalers.
Instead, they lease compute and cloud
capacity from Google, using Google Cloud.
Apple isn’t ignoring AI. Well, in some ways it is.
It’s running AI in a different business model:
On‑device first, cloud second, and
almost no owned datacenter empire.
Apple wisely runs AI where it can on-device, in
their existing infrastructure, but beyond that,
instead of spending hundreds
of billions building out more
data centres, it just rents them.
Okay, so why does the market care?
Apple isn’t spending money,
and is renting AI. So what?
Well, because they control
something more valuable.
If you’ve watched this far, consider
subscribing! It helps the channel and
means you won’t miss future videos.
I think everyone realized that Apple,
despite not spending so much on AI, still
owns one of the most valuable layers of AI.
The layer where the users are.
[Nicolas Cote-Colisson, HSBC]:“Apple
is now at an operational turning point: not
only can the company stay away from the (too)
high capex debate… it is also well placed to
leverage its 2.5 billion installed device base
with its forthcoming revamped Apple Intelligence.”
[Toni Meadows, BRI Wealth Management]: *“Apple is
less exposed to capex intensity and better
positioned to monetize AI via services,
ecosystem lock-in, and hardware upgrades.”*
The economics of this are pretty smart.
OpenAI, for example, has around
900-910 million weekly active users,
95% of them are on the free service.
So they have a -122% operating margin.
But Apple has 2.5 billion active devices.
Even if they all use Apple Intelligence,
Apple's marginal cost per AI prompt is
basically zero. Because it’s running locally.
The silicon, the electricity and the
depreciation all belong to the customer,
who already paid for the iPhone, iPad, etc.
This also cuts the need for them to own
giant amounts of GPU clusters, which can
lose half their value in eighteen months.
But this local AI use is limited,
though this isn’t a bad thing.
Apple Intelligence does carry daily
usage limits, like any other LLM.
iCloud+ subscribers get even more AI use.
But that’s just another way to monetize.
When it starts to cost Apple, aka during
*Private Cloud Compute,* is when they charge.
Then, when users want the most costly AI
use, they just license it from Google,
and charge the user, passing on the cost to
them, while making a little bit of money.
So Apple wins in basically every case.
Unlike other AI companies, who lose money
on free users, and make a little
bit on users who want more AI use.
“While Apple was initially bruised by
many investors for not joining the LLM
investment cycle, investors are coming around
to Apple's industry-leading [free cash flow]”.
The AI moat isn’t really how many GPUs or data
centres it owns, but all the devices it controls.
2.5 billion.
Which means
spend is low, but cash flow is still high.
This means they can return good money to
investors, which is becoming less common nowadays.
That explains why they’ve returned to the
top. Well, they were at the top.
Ironically, this isn’t anything new.
They never wanted to own all the
infrastructure, they wanted to own
the layer with all the margins and behaviour.
And this has basically always been the case.
But, strangely, Apple predicted
the future of AI: Commoditization.
Apple does not need to build the best model. It
only needs multiple companies competing to supply
one. OpenAI, Google, Anthropic, Meta and others
continue racing, model quality rises, prices fall,
supply expands, intelligence commoditizes.
The entire AI industry is actually
going through a massive shift.
This is the exact reason OpenAI is struggling.
[Josh Rowe]: “While Apple didn’t build any AI
infrastructure, they own one of the most valuable
layers. OpenAI, despite committing
to over a trillion in AI spend,
don’t actually own a valuable part of the AI
ecosystem, and perhaps the least valuable.”
It turns out, while Apple controls
the end users, OpenAI controls a
layer which is becoming less and less valuable.
Yes, they’ve still committed to spending so much.
Click this video to learn
the other side of the story.